this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
softball digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size they're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials and an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio for software engineering
radio Amedda in the Salinas Steffen
eewan is a PMC member and one of the
original creators of Apache flink and
co-founder and CTO of data artisans
previously he worked at IBM and
Microsoft on data processing
technologies he holds a PhD from the
Berlin University of Technology with
data artisans and Apache flink Stephan
works on pushing the capabilities and
the adoption of stream processing
technology Stephan even welcome to
software engineering radio thank you
hello there are systems with data
constantly flowing through them
this data can come from different
sources like telemetry or the Internet
of Things as this amount of data keeps
increasing challenges emerge on how to
process it batch and stream are two ways
in which we can process big data in a
talk that you gave in San Francisco you
mentioned that we can understand these
two by asking what changes faster your
data or your query can you explain what
this means so
if you look at the Negev the nature of
Patchen streaming applications batch
applications are applications that take
a a fix of a finite bit of data and lie
or very typically our applications that
take that and you you may want to run
different types of you know different
types of analysis over over this
particular static type of data think for
example of you know like classical data
warehousing use cases you have the other
static piece of data which is what is
currently in your warehouse or you know
even if your warehouse is continuously
ingested it's like a snapshot view of it
and then you run different exploratory
queries based on the result of the first
let's say you drill down certain
dimensions and so on run the next query
um another example is like machine
learning model training where you take
you take a piece of input data you may
partition it in different ways as in
like training and um and validation set
and then um and then you around the
training model but it's in some sense
always the same same data that you base
this on even though you might split it
differently between different trainings
run different training runs so in like
these are kind of applications were the
kind of work that you do changes but
it's always on the on the same on the
same static data set streaming's
is if you wish the the opposite of that
you have you have an application that
you know that continues to run and you
can really think very broadly of what
kind of application that is it can be
something that computes some you know
like some statistics over over what is
you know what is happening in in the in
the data that is being produced mm-hmm
it can it can be you know like an
application like like a web service that
you know XA that bags of X an online
application the the logic there is is
the same kind of logic that runs all the
time but the data that it runs on is
actually it's it's not finite the data
doesn't really exist all before the
application is launched so while the
application exists and stays the same
more and more and more and more data
comes and
keeps changing over time so that's why
why these two are almost the you know
like the the inverse of each other and
in some sense that that boils down to
another interpretation of of matchin
streaming you can you can think of off
streaming or the most defining part of
streaming is actually this aspect of of
continuity of of data being being um
being produced and being processed a
streaming application is an inherently
an application that is not necessarily
bounded towards the end so while it
starts if it doesn't yet have an end of
data where where it's done where it
actually shuts down and says you know my
job is done it's it just stays there in
it it continues to receive to receive
receive events and you know events that
can come from a message queue that can
come from user interaction with it
versus a batch application is like a
it's like a finite job or project it has
a fixed amount of data that that you run
it on so they're like the most defining
difference is is that that streaming is
unbounded towards the end versus with
this batch is not and that like with
that comes comes the fact that that in
batch because the data aesthetic usually
the application changes more often and
in streaming because the data is
unbounded and the like the streaming
application exists before you even know
the end of the the end of the data the
streaming the application usually stays
the same way the data changes are there
characteristics of the applications that
is better if we use the streaming
approach because in a sense we can have
this stream of data coming but we can
just decide to store a big file and then
just do batch processing what is the
advantage of having available this
technology of stream processing for
certain applications
I mean stream processing has a bunch of
very strong advantages which is I think
why it's why it's actually you know
creating such such a big interest at the
moment the first one is quite
straightforward right if you if you
ingest the data first wait until you've
filled up a certain chunk and then say
okay let me create like let me take this
static piece of of the
then run a betcha you're introducing a
delay until you actually run the
computation so for the time that you
know like this this amount of data this
buffer or this block fills up so if
you're you know this run this results
then often in this periodic periodic
batch jobs you ingest for a while and
every day every hour every few minutes
you kick off a certain batch job but it
inherently actually means that the data
is already a little bit stale by the
time the computation runs and a lot of
data is very valuable when it's very
fresh so this or the like getting this
delay down is something people are very
interested in and the best thing you can
actually do is get it to to zero and
just process it as it comes right we
we've seen this trend of periodic batch
jobs trying to become more and more and
more frequent so they act on on fresher
data all the time and then streaming is
like the extreme form of that you don't
even you don't even try to to chop it
into finite sets and then run the stream
sorry run the batch processing
application but you just process the
data exactly immediately as it comes
that is one part of it that like stream
processing really helps with with like
immediately reacting to data when it's
when it's still very fresh when it's
very valuable and for a lot of
application it doesn't even make sense
to react to certain events anymore in
hindsight the other the other aspect to
that is that extra streaming is really a
very natural way to to represent a lot
of problems if you look at how most of
the data is produced it's actually
produced in a like in a continuous
fashion in an somewhat unbounded fashion
right streaming data like we're treating
a problem is a streaming problem matches
that very well if you look at the data
producer like you know like a web
service that that just logs user
interactions and you want to process
that in order to you know like get to
get insights in what is happening in
your new service right now or to build
like a life recommender or so like these
the interactions being continuous
produced over time is really a stream
and if you try to apply a batch
processing for that you come to this to
this point of saying okay so this thing
that is actually created as a stream and
in an unbounded fashion and I have to
introduce like arbitrary outer
boundaries and then and then interpret
each individual you know inch individual
carved out piece as a finer data set
it's a it's actually not as as natural a
thing to do as as just treating it as a
stream and processing it as a stream and
I think it's mainly been done
historically because of immaturity of
stream processing technology there was
just no other way than to say let's
let's cut the bet that stream into
pieces and treat each each piece as a
batch but a stream a stream processing
technology continues to mature we
actually see that there are a lot of
people are very interested in like again
adopting this quite natural paradigm of
processing a stream as history let's
talk a little bit about that you
mentioned batching was in part used
because stream processing was still
immature so I just want to understand if
there's somebody that has this all this
data coming from the web service like
you mentioned and they want to set up
batch processing what would be the
components of this architecture for
example where can the data be stored
would it be like a distributed file
system and just pretty much what would
they need to do to set it up as closely
as as if it where stream processing
processing but not quite there yet
I think if you look at the somewhat
historical evolution of technology I
think this this actually goes goes back
quite a bit you can see that you know
with with relational databases people
have tried to to do the same thing I
continues ingestion or you know as data
is produced you immediately insert it
into the database and then you
periodically run your analytical queries
on the database this is a form of like
streaming ingestion into a store and
then running batch processing just
within this like or closed monolithic
piece of the database and you know some
companies have actually adopted that
long ago and like somewhat successfully
even if it had quite significant costs
in many cases but I guess if you if you
look at the like at the other more
modern trends the big data way of doing
this it's it's probably more like you
like you said right you have something
like a continuous ingestion into a
distributed file system you know with
projects I guess the first ones to do
that were projects like Apache flume or
so and then he would have you
would have something else that kicks off
the the batch job that analyzes the data
and the in the distributed file system
yeah so for for streaming streaming
ingestion and then batch processing to
approximate stream processing I think
that that would probably be the approach
and if you're if you're trying to
approximate stream processing more and
more you end up at trying to decrease
the batch size more and more until you
know the batches become just very very
small and you might end up with
something like mini batching even so you
mentioned like in the very early days it
was just a matter of setting up database
related for this for gathering the data
and just adding the data to a table or
something and then processing that and
now we have distributed file systems we
have patchy foam what are some of the
bottlenecks so floom floom was one of
the very early technologies I think
probably these days if you if you ingest
into a file system there's there's very
different ways to do this it's either
you know either you actually use a
stream processor directly to ingest into
into the file system and do some if you
wish some pre-processing on the way or
you you may use things like like like
tools that work with the with the
message queues and directly right from
message queues to the file systems like
tools around you know things like like a
calf car or also like event hub or pops
up and so on a lot of them come with
connectors that are like mainly intended
to to do ingestion and revenge
processing because it still is a big use
case I see so what you're saying is the
one where you mentioned that is just
about to form and not just to be a file
system like it's still pretty in the
early days if you try to do that now I
think these were the like the first this
were the early days of yeah of taking
streams putting streams into a battery
storage and then computing over the
battery storage yes well where some of
the bottlenecks that could be hit back
then if if you're trying to go with this
approach of doing batches more
frequently as a system keeps growing I
mean a pet shop a pet shop depending on
how you set it up often has has a
problem of I think you can call this
like broken boundary
so let's say you have you have a batch
job to interact a sorry true to analyze
sessions with which users interact with
with a certain service that's that's
very often it's very often something you
need at the beginning right you just
need to actually gather you the user
sessions and together like a users
behavior within that session and that is
that is input then to some some later
processing step like you know like
training training a model to predict um
what what users what would be
interesting interested in depending on
what they interact with the problem is
if you if you actually chop your data
stream at some point you're inevitably
going to break a lot of these sessions
right so you you have to put some logic
in place to kind of repair the
boundaries to carry some results from
the previous batch also into the next
batch in in that way trying to you know
carry the in progress sessions into them
into the next one um if you start
decreasing your your batch sizes more
and more and more you can easily come to
the point that this that that each batch
doesn't just this way more it just
either repeats a lot of work or it has
to spend a lot of work like carrying
over information from the previous batch
and you almost come to the point that
warming up the actual contribute
computation is much more effort than the
computation and that is where you know
if you actually get then come to the
model and say yeah let's actually just
treat the computation as continuous we
just you know like we keep the
information we keep the state in there
all the time and just continuously
compute on on this just for goes all of
these problems I see and the ones that
you highlight it is the batch is
essentially just one piece but because
you're doing them smaller and more
frequent there's this additional steps
of stitching together previous
information and using that for the
current computation is what you're
saying right yeah this is just in order
to let's say if you want to approximate
like more closer closer real-time
computation with batch processing
there's um there's a lot of of
applications that that have the the
requirement to choosers operate in and
with a very low latency where it's it's
completely completely infeasible to even
start up the batch processing job within
the
that they usually need to deliver the
answer in right so a lot of a lot of
fraud detection anomaly detection like
network intrusion detection and so on
where you really have to answer within
like sub-second
often even sub hundred milliseconds and
so on it's completely infeasible to like
first do the ingestion and then kick off
the batch job for these applications
it's really essential that the
computation is online and immediately
reacts to the data as it comes in but
even for applications that don't have
this like very hard low latency
requirements if you start true to make
make the batches shorter and shorter and
shorter at some point in time you're
paying a lot of a lot of overhead price
in be bet with B that with scheduling B
that with you know loading pre-warming
pre loading like previous results and so
on in order to continue on them you
mentioned if you have a system where you
value data that is fresh like for
example from anomaly detection or
intrusion that's a point where you can
switch to a stream processing
architecture because the architecture
with batching even if you do it more
frequent we talked about some of the
issues with that but there's a cost
issue where costs can get very high at
where other point I think there's there
are many cases where you actually want
to switch to that before before actually
coming to this like very very low
latency case like like I said before
extremis really a very good paradigm
every time the data that you're
processing is really continuously
produced data and you have this this
kind of piece of work that is the same
work that you apply to all the data
right be that routing it to a different
point in your in your infrastructure
like ingesting it into storage is one
one one example of like a continuous
piece of work that you do on changing
data as it as it changes over time but
also indexing it filtering it
pre-processing it searching it for R for
anomalies continuously updating certain
you know like certain like models or
certain state that you keep around for
let's say for users that interact with
your with your website or for our other
customers all these things that you
to Drew continuously all the time and
that work on data that is continuously
produced like this these are natural
streaming applications actually and even
if they don't require a super low
latency case there's a there's really
with maturing stream processing
technology there isn't there isn't
really a reason anymore to not treat
them like that the reason to treat them
with batches I think were mainly
historic when batch processing was
vastly more efficient than stream
processing was but that is not quite the
case anymore so there's there's really a
very good point to start like just
treating streams or streams and modeling
the modeling the processing as streaming
applications so you're saying if you
have a component that's continuously
generating data that in itself is enough
to switch to streaming what about scale
is there a certain scale where we should
start thinking about stream processing
or just with the idea of we have
something continuously being generated
let's just wire up a stream processing
architecture to it I think in in many
ways as soon as you have this continuous
data continuous processing continuous
computation this is this is a good good
reason to actually start to start
thinking about a streaming architecture
so we see we see users like from our
perspective users of Apache flink that
use stream processing on as many nodes
as like one two three notes for for very
low volume for very wallet low volume
data streams or as many as 10,000 nodes
for extremely high volume data streams
so the technology really works on very
small scale and very large scale and it
it is really all about modeling your
problem as a or modeling your
application as a stream processing
application that's something that does
continuous processing versus you know a
certain scale that says Oh at this scale
I should really go rather for stream
processing versus at that scale I should
rather go for batch processing earlier
when we were talking about very early
days architectures you mentioned that
one improvement in particularly in the
batching one but it can still be used
for streaming architecture is this
pub/sub and message queues
can you explain what pub/sub is
if you look at data being extreme
engaging being produced and being being
made available for for processing it's
very often quite beneficial to make to
decompose the stream processing part and
the leg the data producer part and I'd
put put the data somewhere where it can
be consumed amiss in a streaming fashion
but you know it could also be it can
also be buffered there for a while it
can be reckoned in in case we you know
we have a failure in the application I
need to like redo a little bit of work
and and these systems that that there
are some water let's you can think of
them as being the the equivalent of the
of the distributed file system in the
streaming space where the distributed
file system are the storage for batch
these systems or the storage for
streaming those yeah those those play
the role of being the very often like
the the first wants to to receive the
data and to buffer and store it at least
for for a certain while and those are
very often either pop subsystems or or
logs
I see so what you're saying is one way
of structuring the streaming
architecture is to have this section
that handles data producing in this
other piece that's more about the
stream processing part and that it that
in it senses the puffs of your
publishing the data you're producing it
and the sub which is the subscriber is
just taking that data and doing some
computation of it so at a higher level
there's two main pieces in a stream
architecture right - there are two main
pieces I would say probably more if you
if you look more towards the edges and I
think they're there interestingly very
very very analogous to the pieces of a
batch processing architecture in a in a
batch processing architecture you have
better storage like a distributed file
system you have the batch processors to
do the computation you often have a
piece that does the you know I take the
data the data ingestion and you often
have something that takes the result of
the batch processor and there's
something with it either you know that
continues it to push it push it down the
like further downstream steps of the
workflow or or presents it in the form
of a dashboard or something like that
and in the in the streaming architecture
that's really very similar there the
producers the producers typically write
into some form of log or message queue
which is the storage piece and at least
the let's say short-term storage piece
short-term mid-term depending on on what
exactly you use and then there's the
computational part the stream processor
which is the analog to the batch
processor and then usually have some
form of off system that takes the
results and yeah there's something with
it the system you know and the results
can be really anything the results can
be actions that are triggered and the
infrastructure by RPC or dashboards that
present like real-time analytics or you
know just be storage systems or other
streams for for downstream consumption I
see you mentioned the message queue is
short-term storage right yeah so the way
that most of these most of these let's
say message queues or logs work these
days is that they they have a certain
they have kind of a like a limited
lifetime there's some projects that try
to work around that but the I think the
the the state of the of the art like the
popular projects all have a
have a limited a limited storage time or
limited storage capacity so when when
the data first goes into the log or into
the message queue it stays in there for
for a while for for various applications
to consume and there's very often a like
one of these applications that that
consume the data is very often you can
think of it as some form of backup
application that that takes it may be
filters it compresses it for some form
of long term archival in in some form of
bulk storage like again a distributed
file system this makes you know this
makes in many ways sense to use the
distributed file system there because at
this at this time
you know when the data actually is
accessed from there it's it's no longer
fresh data anyways so it's it's not
really important to to serve it from a
message queue and there are projects
that try to you know combine these
pieces message queues that age out data
to distributed file systems
automatically and when Dana reaches his
message queue has it previously
undergone a transformation or is it just
directly putting the data the way it was
formatted for example for a log or is
there up a step prior to that so when
the when the data hits the log or the
message queue like the logs and message
queues are really the are the store the
data storage both for for the afresh
let's say the initial raw data as it
comes directly from the producing
service but very much also for the data
that comes out of the first
pre-processing steps so very many setups
that we see have have have a have a log
or a message queue just for the raw data
stream that have a stream processing job
that is initial tech initial filtering
transformation cleanup in Richmond and
then writes it into multiple other
message queues and locks for different
downstream consumers and then you know
there may be different consumers that do
some other massaging of the data and
write it again to a logger message queue
for even further downstream consumers so
it it's really you know and in the same
way as one batch processing job can
write a result to the files distributed
file system and then the next batch
processing job can pick it up from there
in the same way stream processing jobs
can
pull their source data from a message
queue and write it down stream to a
message queue again what's an example of
a piece of data that reaches the message
queue just to illustrate what are some
of the things that are can be logged by
systems we can talk about it in terms of
that web service system were the anomaly
detection or some other application so
it can be really almost any event that
that reflects something happening right
it can be machine generated events so
for for some use cases that we see it's
actually just server's reporting or
microservices reporting what they just
did and it's just it's just used for you
know to to maintain metrics of what is
internally happening it could be
something like you know a credit card
transaction that that hits the message
queue as in okay somebody is trying to
do this transaction and the the
streaming application now computes a a
let's say a risk score do we believe
this is a fraudulent attempt or is it a
valid attempt it can be a user hovering
over an item on the website which which
feeds back into the message queue and
into the stream processor that then you
know updates the updates the users
behavior model which is again input to
to the website computing what to show
next like which product to suggest next
or so it can be a an event generated by
by an app like you know like a Geo
coordinate that goes to the message
queue in the stream processor consumes
the stream of like off of things with
with geo coordinates to actually try to
compute traffic models of a certain
region so the it's really very it's very
broad what it could be let's talk about
the next step in the architecture which
is a computational component when we're
dealing with streams
how can computation be done in this
continuous data so in in in some sense
there's like the the first pieces is
very simple and an application that just
reacts to events as an application that
just either receives you know receives
events being pushed their way be that
you know in as being in reactive
application as reacting to
to RPC calls even or something that just
just posted on the message queue and
does something with the event and like
this this kind of simple case I think
you know has has been around for a while
the the the tricky pieces how do you
implement a system that that computes
over these events just that in like in
in a very consistent way like in a photo
in a very fault tolerant way let's let's
assume the simple case we're reading
from a message queue doing some
computation and writing to a message
making sure that whenever something
fails we do not actually accidentally do
repeat it the repeated work like we're
not publishing an event while we recover
from the failure that we have published
before that can create wrong results
downstream and the even more challenging
porters once we're not looking at this
in a stateless fashion anymore once
we're looking at at applications that
take an event but they can't really look
at the event in isolation they need to
understand the context let's say the
event represents a user interaction they
need to to have the context of what were
the other interactions that the user did
before um in order to you know model
it's it's session behavior or if the if
the event is a is a credit card
transaction and we need to take other
context or data into account like what
what other transactions are ongoing at
the same point in time let's say between
the same source and target accounts or
what was what was the other previous
behavior of the user you know for a
certain type of for a certain type of
transfer whenever we need this
contextual information and it it very
often is not just like reading this
contextual information from some
auxiliary database but taking the event
take processing it with the context in
mind and also updating this contextual
information whenever we have this kind
of pattern we we come talk about like
stateful processing stateful stream
processing here and like this is the
this is really the much more challenging
part because what what you can think
about is all of a sudden this
computation now has the has both the
role of the computation and of data
consistency in in in some way right
because they're they're maintaining the
the state of the application the
contextual information for each
individual request that the application
in conjunction with the computation and
maintaining maintaining a big consistent
view on that without sacrificing
intellect performance and scalability
that has been if you wish like the the
grand challenge of stream processing
over the last years and the like
efficient solutions to that problem or
what I think mates reprocessing
technology you really take off
so this computational component is the
one that would have that logic for
gathering the context is that correct um
I wouldn't call it gathering the context
it if you do if you do stateful stream
processing think of it as you you just
you just some application that some
programmer wrote in be that you know
Java C sharp C Python or so and you hear
you're handling a bunch of a bunch of
events happening you know somebody
somebody sends you an event calls calls
a function and and you're just treating
it you're treating this and you're
you're trying to to also maintain the
context and you'd probably you know have
some local variables where you store
okay I've seen so many events for that
user let's say in the last in the last
minute I've seen so many events of that
per certain type in in the last in the
last day and so on something that you
would you know you'd store it in a local
variable um if you just put a very
simple standalone application if if you
then of course try to make this fault
tolerant you know like an application
that that can handle failures that can
that can can recover that is resilient
then very very often you don't store
this in in local variables anymore right
so what you do is you try to connect the
database and you say all these things
that you know I need actually to be able
to recover it I store them in the
database so whenever an event comes um
you know looking something up in a
database doing some computation and
writing something back in the database
you may not do this explicitly it may be
you know hidden from you by frameworks
that that do that in the background but
in some sense that is that is what what
happened for most applications that just
reacted to to events to to real time
data and the the big thing about stream
processing is you don't have this
anymore the separation of of
computing and storage but you have
actually a stateful computational
component that that does this
computation and state management
consistently together for you so it um
it's really every thinking of the of the
whole architecture of of computation and
state management and this yeah this has
I think this has this has both big
implications on real-time data
processing because it is much faster
than talking to a database in the
background it's much faster than if you
talk to the database in the background
it here you're almost back to the
original architecture of you know events
come you ingest them in the database and
then you try to compute something with
either you know if you compute in real
time you may have to find some triggers
on the database or so or you frequently
run queries but instead of doing that
you really let the application directly
handle the data and the the streaming
application that has to worry about the
fault tolerance and recovery and
consistency of the data and the the
stream processors giving you the giving
you the-- you know like the building
blocks that take this heart challenge
that's all that heart challenge for you
to actually do the duty to the
consistency and persistence and recovery
and you know in the same way also the
scaling our turn scaling up that is that
is really the core of of stream
processing technology and we talked a
lot about like applications and
databases and this this is also where I
think this is you know where this is
starting to to make a big impact it it
has started to be something more than
just a faster way or a more low latency
way of data processing as we do it with
batch processing it's actually started
to become a different way of of building
data-driven applications rather than
having like a stateless application
server that talks to a database whenever
an event comes whenever a user sends a
request or something like that you
really fuse those two things together
into a into a stateful stream processing
application that that reacts to you know
like the events coming in the stream and
and manages the state itself digital
ocean is the easiest cloud platform to
deploy manage and scale applications of
any size we're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that custom
love with thousands of in-depth
tutorials in an active community we
provide the support you need
digitalocean stands out of the crowd due
to its simplicity and high performance
with no billing surprises try
digitalocean for free by getting a 100
dollar infrastructure credit at doco /
SC radio yes I really see the value of
adding this state part to stream
processing particularly in the case that
you mention about credit card
transactions or taking into account what
else has a user done before for the
stateless one I just want to understand
what would be an example where it
wouldn't really matter to take this
context into account I think very simple
examples of of status applications maybe
you know stream processing applications
that just route data so you're receiving
a raw data stream and let's say for
every event that comes in the raw stream
you're you're let's say filtering it re
encoding it and you're writing it to
another a message queue downstream and
you know maybe writing a copy to the
distributed file system storage for for
archival in this case you really treat
each event individually you don't need
to know any contextual information
across events these applications are
pretty much stateless they may maintain
you know like a minimal amount of State
and the sources and sinks to to
coordinate
you know like avoiding duplicates on
recovery but that is more like
implementation specifics on how how the
how the consistent integration with the
source and target systems works the epic
the core application itself doesn't
doesn't maintain contextual state so
things like you know streaming real-time
ETL where you don't pre aggregate but
you really only you really only filter
and transform there would be an example
what I'm trying to understand is those
data from different parts of the
application end up in the same message
queue for processing even if it's not
very related to each other for example
we have the credit card transactions
information where we can also have the
about user behavior in in our web
application or something like that I
think in many in many ways yeah the
setups we see use very similar like it
locks a message queues for for these
events because there's there's not not
really a need to treat them to treat
them differently right and I can have a
first order approximation they're just
all bytes that describe something that
happened and that carry that information
and also their availability should
trigger something right these are
they're like two main components of an
event carry some information in a
trigger some action and all of them
exhibit that behavior what what exactly
you know they're their purpose their
meaning is at this plaque for for the
rough architecture that doesn't really
make any difference no you're one of the
founders and creators of Apache flink
which is an open-source stream
processing framework can you explain in
more detail what it consists of yeah so
Apache fling is a it's a pretty broad
system these days it's it has grown it
has grown a lot it is in its core a
system to do exactly what we said before
to compute over data streams in a in a
stateful fashion that's it's that's
basically it's its core mission now I've
had a fling takes a very broad
interpretation to that so over over the
course of this discussion we you know we
talked about batch processing we talked
about new hot stream processing as
faster batch processing faster analytics
we talked about stream processing kind
of being a model to to create
applications and Apache flink really
tries to take this very very broad
interpretation to what stream processing
is stream processing is the unifying
paradigm to to do any form of like
continuous analytics and to like
continuous applications and it it were
example interprets batch processing as a
special form of stream processing batch
processing is or stream processing is
computing over an unbounded amount of
data with content with continuously
existing logic but in some sense batch
processing is is a bit of a special case
of that just right so instead of having
an infinite data stream you have a
finite data stream that is your final
data set and whether the application
actually continues to run for long or
short and then you start another
application doesn't really matter to
flink so in that case it actually does
batch processing as well and it it
actually it doesn't just look at batch
processing as is only doing stream
processing with slightly different
parameters but it also has has certain
optimizations in the system for you know
like assumptions that you can make if
you if you work on bounded data versus
unbounded data for example you can you
can do different forms of scheduling you
can use different forms of data
processing algorithms if you know that
you're working on unbounded data it
gives you it gives you the abilities to
think gives you very much the abilities
to to model stream processing in a
highly in a highly flexible and
expressive way so one one core part of
stream processing of building stream
processing applications is treating of
data completeness and latency I think
you can think of it like that if you
only look at batch processing and batch
processing you have a fixed set of data
and that is all you ever have and you
have it all at once if you wish in
stream processing data comes
continuously and for a lot of a lot of
results there is there's this this
trader of like how long do I wait for my
result it's it might be a little more
accurate if I wait a little longer
you know if I'm if I'm if I want to
let's take the example of some mobile
application that you know sense sense
event into our engine and these these
events might you know they might be
affected by some transport problems or
so you know coverage issues you know
they may not be sent all immediately but
they might be sent in bundles in order
to save some data and then when you
actually do analytics at any point in
time you can say let me wait a little
longer and I can take a little more data
into account to really understand what
happened within this hour because some
data might still be
on the other hand you might not want to
wait for long because that would hold
back your results so like very like this
is one of the one of the absolute core
elements of I think we have time data
processing in general where stream
processing in Apache flame gives you
really good tools to model that for so
this is this is the very the very core
of language continuous streaming really
embrace the nature of all the streaming
of all the streaming questions giving
you the right tools to true to model the
application doing batch processing as a
special form of streaming room stream
processing very robust very scalable
link powers some of the largest stream
processing setups in the world that we
personally actually know of and it it
tries to to also innovate in like in
other areas like for example how do you
how do you specify stream processing
applications right you can specify them
as applications in Java Scala and flink
but there's also very active development
on on the layer for streaming SQL so it
kind of comes with a with an
interpretation of what SQL means in the
streaming world and like very like a
very powerful implementation of of SQL
that actually has a very consistent
meaning between the batch world and the
streaming world but still comes with
like with certain extensions or built-in
functions that make a lot of streaming
use cases very well representable in in
SQL so it's really a passive link is
this is this big project like
computation over data streams as they
are at the heart and then then all the
things around it that that you need to
act to to model the applications with
different IP eyes with right tools and
spending the whole breadth of the
spectrum batch processing you know
continuous analytics continuous data
driven applications what does the
tooling look like for what you talked
about just now where you're trying to
determine at one point do you stop and
provide our results when you like you
said you might need just a little bit
more data to
or do something meaningful I just want
to understand in what ways can users
specify this or does the system
determine that part this is basically
the core of of the Aventa model that
flink implements which is like highly
inspired by the data flow model from
from Google and Apache beam the the core
part of that is first of all making the
switch from what is called like event
processing time to proper event time so
we're in like events are interpreted by
the time that they were created or
stored they're not interpreted as
belonging to the time that they're
processed in the stream processor and
that that is actually not that's
actually not a big deal if you think
about it right this is pretty much like
like in in most batch processing systems
and in SQL you know there's a field in
the event that's a timestamp and in
order to compute what has happened per
per hour you sort of round the timestamp
down to the full hour and group by it so
like having first-class support for that
in the stream processor it just makes
sense especially if you also look at
bench processing as your use cases right
the interesting part is when you have
that and you the stream processors very
aware of this this timestamp that is
that is important it's not just
something that's hidden from the stream
processor it has to be aware of that
time then you give the user the the way
to define a like what we call
watermarking strategy and that really
encapsulates this this note this
trade-off between latency and
completeness right you can think of the
the watermark being the point when when
you say ok my data is now complete
you're a Stickley complete and i want to
want to act on it now and how aggressive
you define this to be depending on you
know like the correct characteristics of
your data stream this really
encapsulates the trade-off that is one
part another part is is for example that
that that flink offers like a very
flexible programming abstractions to
interact with like with timers that are
you know triggered by either clocks or
watermarks and so on in order
to to allow you to say okay I'm I'm
acting on data I'm acting on let's say
on watermark but I'm also acting the
latest at this particular point in time
you can take events you can schedule
them to be reprocessed later for example
when when you have a little a bit of a
more complete view of your data and you
know all those tools playing together is
is basically the torch and that that you
have an order to to model this behavior
between a latency and completeness I see
and if I understand this correctly you
mentioned event time an event processing
time event time would be the one right
when the data is generated right by an
IOT device or something in some sense it
is whatever time you assign the event
initially it's okay quite often when the
event was produced it might also be the
time when the event you know hit the
gateway server it might be the time when
the event was first written into the
message queue its whatever time you saw
in the event the important thing is it
has to be a stable time and it it should
really it should reflect something about
the event not about when you launched
the job that processes the event and the
processing time will that be when it
reaches the computational component like
flink
or yeah the processing time is really
pretty much work lock time when it is
the time when it it reaches an a
specific operator and in in many ways
the like applications they say if you
just want a simple application you might
be completely okay with just saying you
know I'm aggregating my events in
Windows by event time I have a watermark
that is either perfect because you know
my when stream is decently well behaved
and I can encapsulate that in the
watermark generator regeneration
strategy or I have a heuristic watermark
and and you're done you know this is
this is what produces your your output
results and you know if the watermark
falls a little behind and the latency
increases it's okay you're dealing with
that if you're if you're doing very
sophisticated applications that have
like very hard real-time requirements
you very often take processing time into
account and say okay
I also need to
to take into account that you know if
event time if the watermark I'm
signaling me signaling me reasonable
completeness if this actually takes too
long I actually want to act anyways just
based on on a local clock when the event
first comes I may say you know defer to
later to when the data is more complete
but also no longer than 100 milliseconds
and in this way you can have combined
both notions of time in order to create
something that that trades of
completeness and latency earlier you
mentioned that another part that you're
working on an apache fling is defining
what c SQL means in this context what
i'm curious of is you work with well
fling has been used by clients like
Netflix Alibaba what are examples of
queries that can be done to streams so
so let me take take back a step to
answer that question
so the yeah the the interpretation of of
SQL in the streaming space is actually
is a really kind of I think a bit a bit
of a newer thing it's it's a fling fling
the fling community is very much
cooperating with the Apache beam
community and with the calcite community
to define that and now our model there
is SQL is inherently defined on tables
so let's actually you know streaming SQL
should also be defined on tables but
exactly in the way that you know classic
SQL is more like batch workload the
table is is viewed as a as a static as a
fixed things
streaming sequel takes a view of the
table as a dynamic thing it's a you know
it's a table that changes over time so
the result of a sequel query that goes
over a static table is a static table
and the result of a sequel query that
goes over a dynamic table is again a
dynamic table and the semantics stay
pretty much exactly the same it's
actually a concept that is somewhat
hidden in in some databases in the form
of materialized views and materialized
few maintenance and some of the more
advanced data warehousing data bases
especially and we kind of took take the
as a as a as a its base semantical model
for for streaming sequel the the
question then becomes a kind of
threefold how do you derive the dynamic
table from a stream of events how do you
turn the result dynamic table into a
stream of events this is kind of a
question how do you how do you connect
through the outside world and this is
where you know like users have quite a
bit of a flexibility to describe how to
derive the table and recreate streams
from the table and then inside SQL it's
all about which computations can
actually work efficiently on on changing
tables to produce a changing table right
you don't want to recompute the SQ at
the SQL queries work every time a change
to the dynamic input table happens we
can theoretically do this but it's not
gonna be very usable at any non-trivial
scale so in some sense all workloads
that lend themselves to be to this
incrementalization so you can
dynamically compute the results based on
changes of the input those are those are
very good fits for stream processing
concretely there's a lot of a lot of
queries for that mate for which that
makes sense
some of them are not yet possible in
flink especially if it comes to the
point that they use very complex forms
of let's say sub queries and correlated
subqueries that you know the optimizer
cannot rewrite them there's no good
efficient way to like incrementally
update the results so those those don't
lend themselves for streaming sequel
execution but we've actually seen that
like within within some of the bigger
users of link like Alibaba like uber
like Yelp and and lyft there's like a
lot of these a lot of the use cases
therefore stream processing actually
match ask y'all pretty pretty decently
there's there's a there's a good mix
there some like very kind of advanced
special applications that they that they
implement directly let's say on the more
low-level streaming if your eyes to to
really exploit very specific
capabilities of link very often these
are the also the heavy lifting jobs the
UM the ones that run it like a very
large scale that do something like very
specific and important
is that say the there's the bulk of of
applications that they do some
processing that contribute to to some
service that actually are a pretty good
match for SQL so I wouldn't go to the
point to say you know SQL is all you
need for streaming but it's probably a
good 8020 principle there you know you
can probably with a good sequel support
capture 80% of the of the common use
cases and then 20% you offer to actually
go down get on the stack to like a more
low-level API which gives you better
control of what happens when I was
researching for this interview I saw
that Apache flame has three abstractions
we've talked about two of them the
analytics component we also talked about
stateful applications you mentioned
right now the the other abstraction
which is more of the low-level that
explores specifics of flink
can you explain a little bit what this
means this low level abstraction so one
thing to maybe point out at the
beginning is these are these are in some
sense you can think of them as slightly
different abstractions but they all kind
of blend together or interact very well
right so a single program can actually
use all of these together you can start
out in SQL and then you can say the
result of this dynamic table I converted
to a data stream then I do some
operation on like classical data stream
windowing some computations and then I'm
using some more low-level piece like
that gives me more raw access to state
and time the I guess the the API is that
Europe were referring to we're really
the like streaming API versus the
low-level
process API and actually from thing if
you look at the fling codebase they're
really within the same API the
lower-level piece is just something that
exposes a little more the raw
ingredients is and on which other
operations are built so if you if you
think of of streaming as as a processing
paradigm that takes a stream of events
and then treats a lot of events together
for example by defining
some things like you know give me the
give me the average time a user
interacts with the service you know like
you built a user session you compute how
long this is compute the average let's
assume we're computing this in the data
stream API not in in SQL for now this is
really a a bit of a computation where
you you don't look all that much at
individual events you're really looking
at all these events together
you're more thinking about this stream
as a whole the more you actually go
through like a very complex application
with with sophisticated business logic
the more often it is actually the case
that you receive an individual event and
you're doing very specific very specific
logic are depending on this individual
event so for example based on based on
the type of the event handling it
differently based on some some some
fields of the event treating it
immediately or deferring it to later or
so on and this is what is what this
lower level abstraction gives you right
it gives you a nice way to say give me
an event give me access to give me
access to time so give me access to time
meaning let me actually understand what
is current processing time what is
current event time let me get your
timers that call me back when a certain
event time has been reached even you
know taking the event and and and
putting it in such a timer and say just
give me the event back actually when a
certain event time has been reached a
very raw access to to interact with
state and so on rather than state being
implicitly handled by you know windows
and window aggregates and so on this is
more than low-level abstraction and and
Anna if we actually look at the use
cases of think we've kind of seen seen
things kind of the more you were doing
analytics the more you gravitate to the
let's say data stream or SQL API and the
more you're building data-driven
applications the more people tend to
gravitate to the to the low-level api to
the very raw you know access to event
processing time and and stage that seems
to be a pattern to get more
customization in that case is one reason
right to get more customization of like
of the lack of the pipeline as a whole
yeah exactly
but yeah
the more you deal with applications you
model more you worry about the
individual event and I think the more
you deal with analytics the more you've
really looking at groups of events
windows of events you know they're of
course they're individual steps like
filtering and and you know event
transformations or so on that where
events can be transformed individually
or so but like the big picture is you're
really interested in the the sum of
events rather than very custom logic for
individual event the last question that
I want to ask you is about the next wave
of stream processing what are some of
the areas where you see architectures
evolving stream computation evolving I
think there is various areas where
stream processing stream processing is
still evolving like on the application
API side
I think SQL streaming SQL still is
actually still evolving in it in itself
even though the the model is semantics
the definition is actually quite like
quite simple and quite complete in
itself if you actually look at how do
you how do you make this usable for a
lot of common use cases they're they're
a bunch of you know constructs you may
want to add and you can actually add
them you know net without possibly by
extending the sequel standard but
possibly also by you know like using
certain like crafty ways of using the
existing sequence standard masking them
as you the essence on this there's a bit
of work for example we're doing an in
flink in order to get get typical like
join and enrichment semantics that are
very common in stream processing feel
like very natural in SQL so on these on
this application api layer there's quite
a bit of work a piece of work that that
somewhat related to that that we did
outside apache flink that the company
that the original creators of apache
filling found it data artisans that
we're working on is actually we've built
a system for you can think of it like
running distributed asset transactions
over streaming data transactions that
take you know not not an individual
video aqui or so into a counter an
individual row but really in like a
multi row few so like without diving
into the details it's a little bit like
opening up stateful stream processing
from the capabilities let's say of
compute plus a key value store to
compute cluster relational database
which is which is quite a bit more
powerful I think this is this is a very
interesting direction also in which and
which stream processing still can can
develop going back to the open source to
the work in an open source in in stream
processing itself one thing where stream
processing is still where where they can
still be today acquire a reason to use
batch processing rather than stream
processing is if you wish resource
efficiency because batch processors
still tend to be a bit more dynamic in
their resource utilization
you know they schedule more fine-grained
tasks on fine-grained finite pieces of
data which in many setups leads to fewer
resource consumption compared to like
long-running streaming jobs so there's
quite a bit of effort going in the
filling community to to introduce more
in like automated scaling automated
adjustment to to resource needs I think
this is going to be it's going to be one
of the last big things were where batch
processors have a certain like advantage
over stream processors there's a whole
lot of work going in providing a more
unified view of that by chance stream
processing while the data flow model
suggests really good way to do this in
the api's there's still quite a bit of
work needed I think on the storage side
and on the runtime side to get this
really unified behavior that you know
stream processors when they work on
historic data even if they they're not
really put into a batch mode they can
still they can still exploit some of
these advantages of bounded data and
then finally there's always you know the
work to make to make things like more
scalable faster recovery zero downtime
upgrades all this all this work that
becomes interesting once you actually
say hey we have the stream processing
technology that you know you know
actually is a really cool way to build
applications let's now build really high
the available highly critical real-time
applications with that you know and the
characteristics that you actually need
what to start doing applications that
need that need a lot of nines of
availability Stephan thank you for
taking the time to come on the show it's
been great talking to you thank you very
much my pleasure digitalocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/sc radio thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se Radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening